<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://alanpapalia.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://alanpapalia.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2025-07-11T14:45:13+00:00</updated><id>https://alanpapalia.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Advice for PhD students</title><link href="https://alanpapalia.github.io/blog/2025/phd-advice/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Advice for PhD students" /><published>2025-07-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alanpapalia.github.io/blog/2025/phd-advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alanpapalia.github.io/blog/2025/phd-advice/"><![CDATA[<p>There’s a lot of great advice out there for PhD students. Here I try to compile
some of the best advice I’ve come across, along with my own thoughts on the
matter. This is a living document, and I will update it as I find more advice or
as my own views evolve.</p>

<p><strong>Last updated:</strong> July 8, 2025</p>

<h1 id="meta-phd-and-broad-phd-advice">Meta-PhD and Broad-PhD Advice</h1>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://greatresearch.org/2013/08/23/why-get-a-ph-d/">Why Get a PhD?</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://greatresearch.org/2013/08/14/managing-your-advisor/">Managing Your Advisor</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://alanpapalia.github.io/blog/2025/philip-guo-phd-tips/">Philip Guo’s tips for PhD students</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://greatresearch.org/2013/09/13/cultivating-your-research-taste/">Cultivating Your Research Taste</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.cs.virginia.edu/~robins/YouAndYourResearch.html">The classic Richard Hamming “You and Your Research” talk</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://greatresearch.org/2013/09/20/research-patterns/">Research Patterns</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.alextamkin.com/essays/tips-for-new-researchers">Alex Tamkin’s tips for researchers</a></li>
</ul>

<h1 id="persistence-and-motivation">Persistence and Motivation</h1>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.jeanyang.com/posts/genius-fallacy/">Jean Yang’s the Genius Fallacy</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://jxyzabc.blogspot.com/2016/03/the-angst-overhead.html">Jean Yang’s The Angst Overhead</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://jxyzabc.blogspot.com/2016/09/five-things-more-important-about.html">Jean Yang’s Five Things More Important About a Research Project Than Being in Love</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://calnewport.com/the-passion-trap-how-the-search-for-your-lifes-work-is-making-your-working-life-miserable/">Cal Newport’s “The Passion Trap”</a></li>
</ul>

<h1 id="writing-and-communication">Writing and Communication</h1>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://greatresearch.org/2013/10/04/presenting-a-technical-talk/">Presenting a Technical Talk</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://greatresearch.org/2013/10/11/storytelling-101-writing-tips-for-academics/">Storytelling 101: Writing Tips for Academics</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://greatresearch.org/2013/09/06/you-and-your-research-proposal/">You and Your Research Proposal</a></li>
</ul>

<h1 id="reading-and-reviewing">Reading and Reviewing</h1>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://greatresearch.org/2013/10/18/the-paper-reviewing-process/">Reading and Reviewing</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research" /><category term="skills" /><category term="research" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A collection of advice for PhD students.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Philip Guo’s Tips for PhD Students</title><link href="https://alanpapalia.github.io/blog/2025/philip-guo-phd-tips/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Philip Guo’s Tips for PhD Students" /><published>2025-07-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alanpapalia.github.io/blog/2025/philip-guo-phd-tips</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alanpapalia.github.io/blog/2025/philip-guo-phd-tips/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="philip-guos-tips-for-phd-students">Philip Guo’s Tips for PhD Students</h1>

<p>Since this page is no longer maintained - I tried to copy what I could into this
page. To be honest, I’m not sure if this is exactly what was on the original
page, but these are all points that are worth considering and it is useful to understand
the perspective they come from.</p>

<p>As always, think critically and make your own decisions about what works for you.</p>

<h2 id="1-stop-caring-about-classes">1. Stop caring about classes</h2>

<p>Just do what you need to pass.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Only spend time on classes once you’ve made progress on your research.</p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="2-undergrad-versus-phd-research">2. Undergrad versus PhD research</h2>

<p>Every student admitted into PhD programs has a lot of potential for creative research, but very few realize it—not because they’re not smart, but due to lacking resilience, perseverance, metacognition, or self-discipline.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>These traits can be fostered through self-reflection and mentorship.</p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="3-uncertainty-isolation-and-project-scoping">3. Uncertainty, isolation, and project scoping</h2>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Uncertainty:</strong> You don’t know if your hard work will pay off.</li>
  <li><strong>Isolation:</strong> Few people care about what you’re doing.</li>
  <li><strong>Project scoping:</strong> You don’t know how big your paper should be.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>What you should do:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Make consistent progress every day.</li>
  <li>Get mentor feedback every 1–2 weeks.</li>
  <li>Submit papers and get external feedback a few times a year.</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="4-develop-research-taste">4. Develop research taste</h2>

<p>How?</p>

<ul>
  <li>Read good recent papers recommended by your advisor.</li>
  <li>Assist others with their projects.</li>
  <li>Accept that a lot of mediocre work is necessary before developing taste. Keep grinding.</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="5-most-of-the-daily-work-wont-feel-like-research">5. Most of the daily work won’t feel like “research”</h2>

<p>If this happens, stay mindful of the big picture. Don’t get trapped in trivialities.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="6-understand-your-advisor">6. Understand your advisor</h2>

<p>If your advisor is pre-tenure, helping them earn tenure will likely depend on your research output.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="7-there-is-no-perfect-advisor">7. There is no perfect advisor</h2>

<p>People succeed <em>despite</em> their advisor’s imperfections. Don’t rely solely on your advisor for your success.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="8-be-patient">8. Be patient</h2>

<ul>
  <li>The first 3 years of your PhD may not count toward your dissertation.</li>
  <li>No publications after 3 years? Still okay.</li>
  <li>If your advisor is untenured, expect pressure to publish sooner.</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="9-make-professors-want-to-help-you">9. Make professors want to help you</h2>

<p>They want to help students who already know how to do research and need less guidance.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Show your potential to be a good researcher.</p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="10-find-peer-support">10. Find peer support</h2>

<p>PhD isolation is the default. Seek out peers proactively.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="11-avoid-infectious-negativity">11. Avoid infectious negativity</h2>

<p>Even if you’re struggling, try not to spread negativity to others.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="12-be-careful-about-advice-from-senior-students-outside-your-area">12. Be careful about advice from senior students outside your area</h2>

<ul>
  <li>They may not understand your specific challenges.</li>
  <li>But they <em>can</em> offer great advice about navigating your advisor.</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="13-understand-your-job">13. Understand your job</h2>

<p>Your job in a PhD is to <strong>publish high-quality research papers that contribute valuable new knowledge</strong>.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="14-make-yourself-accountable">14. Make yourself accountable</h2>

<p>Be accountable to:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Other people (e.g., postdocs or collaborators),</li>
  <li>Deadlines (e.g., conference submissions, talks),</li>
  <li>Structures (e.g., lab meetings).</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="15-develop-a-fixed-work-schedule">15. Develop a fixed work schedule</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Always do the most important thing first.</li>
  <li>Research is your #1 priority—not classes, TA work, or admin.</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>Suggested: Work on research from 8–11am every day, uninterrupted.</p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="16-do-everything-you-can-to-protect-your-mornings">16. Do everything you can to protect your mornings</h2>

<p>Self-explanatory.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="17-politely-turn-down-volunteer-service-work-requests">17. Politely turn down volunteer service work requests</h2>

<p>Self-explanatory.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="18-push-back-against-professors-who-overwork-you-as-a-ta">18. Push back against professors who overwork you as a TA</h2>

<p>Self-explanatory.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="19-keep-moving">19. Keep moving</h2>

<p>If you’re stuck, <strong>tell your advisor or mentors immediately</strong>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Many PhDs fail not from lack of talent, but from getting stuck and demoralized.</p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="20-avoid-the-dreaded-loop-of-despair">20. Avoid the dreaded loop of despair</h2>

<p>Getting stuck → no help → procrastination → worse outcomes.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="21-everyone-is-busyask-for-help-anyway">21. Everyone is busy—ask for help anyway</h2>

<p>If you’ve done your homework, it’s fine to ask busy people for help.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You are not wasting anyone’s time by being prepared and showing desire to grow.</p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="22-managing-your-advisor">22. Managing your advisor</h2>

<p>Advisors are good at <strong>making decisions</strong>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Don’t ask: <em>“What do you think of this draft?”</em>
Ask: <em>“Given A and B, should I use model X, Y, or Z?”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Make it easy for them to help you.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="23-contact-hours">23. Contact hours</h2>

<p>Don’t rely only on metrics like papers or awards.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Instead, track your <strong>daily contact hours</strong> with core research.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Good target:</p>
<ul>
  <li>3–4 hours/day of focused work</li>
  <li>1–2 hours/week of meetings with advisor</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Focus on the action, not the result. The result will come.”</p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="24-my-project-stinks-should-i-quit">24. My project stinks… should I quit?</h2>

<ul>
  <li>If it’s <strong>your own</strong> project: try sticking with it for 3+ months.</li>
  <li>If it’s <strong>someone else’s</strong>: switch if you’ve earned authorship.</li>
  <li>Always aim to gain transferable skills—even if you leave a project.</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>It’s easier to switch projects early in your PhD.</p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="25-writing-papers">25. Writing papers</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Takes <strong>much longer</strong> than expected.</li>
  <li>Don’t worry about quality initially—get content down first.</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>Even 12 pages of junk is better than a blank page.</p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="26-dont-worry-about-big-talkers">26. Don’t worry about big-talkers</h2>

<p>95% of research is done in silence. Don’t feel self-conscious about others who are louder.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Silent excellence is still recognized.</p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="27-dont-compare-yourself-to-other-students">27. Don’t compare yourself to other students</h2>

<p>Self-explanatory.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="28-social-media-and-online-presence">28. Social media and online presence</h2>

<ul>
  <li>You <strong>need</strong> a personal website. It doesn’t need to be fancy.</li>
  <li>Use social media carefully.</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>“It may seem like everyone is winning awards or publishing nonstop. Don’t let that derail you.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“It’s easier to post online than to grind on research. Focus on your real work.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>What matters most for your career is publishing well-regarded papers. Everything else is secondary.</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="29-commonly-observed-struggles">29. Commonly observed struggles</h2>

<ul>
  <li>If no faculty can summarize what you’re doing, your work may not be clear or scoped well.</li>
  <li>It’s helpful to be on your advisor’s <strong>critical path</strong>—it keeps you motivated and aligned.</li>
</ul>

<hr />]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research-skills" /><category term="research" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Words from Philip Guo on how to succeed in a PhD program.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Undergrad Research Philosophy</title><link href="https://alanpapalia.github.io/blog/2025/undergrad-research/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Undergrad Research Philosophy" /><published>2025-07-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alanpapalia.github.io/blog/2025/undergrad-research</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alanpapalia.github.io/blog/2025/undergrad-research/"><![CDATA[<p>This is a document I wrote early on in grad school to help me clarify my
philosophy on working with undergrads. I haven’t really updated it since my
first or second year (2020?), but I still think it captures my beliefs on the
points of undergrad research and what I expect from students.</p>

<hr />

<h1 id="my-undergrad-research-philosophy">My Undergrad Research Philosophy</h1>

<p>If you’re reading this, there’s a high probability that you’re an undergrad who
is interested in research in robotics. That’s great! Robotics is an exciting
field to work in right now, with really bright people and really important
problems we’re trying to solve!</p>

<p>All the flashy demos online make it seem like there aren’t any unanswered
questions in the field, but if you ask around, you’ll discover there’s so much
work left to do—and the field needs bright, energetic minds like you to help
solve them!</p>

<p>I love working with undergrads (and grad students) who are excited to tackle
problems. This document outlines the <em>what</em> and <em>why</em> behind my undergrad
collaborations. I know this is a bit of a read, but if you’re seriously
interested in trying out this research thing, I ask that you give it a genuine
read through. Part of working together is we both are committing time to this
collaboration, which really works best if we’re on the same page as to what that
means.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="resources">Resources</h2>

<p>Before diving into my own ramblings, here are some really great blog posts that
I very much agree with. Before you do anything else, I’d encourage you to read
through these and think about how their ideas sit with your own philosophies. I
don’t think it’s a coincidence that these separate blog posts all came to
relatively similar conclusions about getting the most out of undergrad research.
Based on my own experiences, these ideas extend beyond just research but really
getting the most out of your time as an undergrad in general.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://rosewang2008.github.io/blog/2021/01/03/undergrad-research-advice.html">Rose Wang: <em>Dear future undergraduate researcher</em></a></li>
  <li><a href="https://dblalock.github.io/how-to-undergrad-research/">Davis Blalock: <em>How to undergrad research</em></a></li>
  <li><a href="https://shashank-srikant.github.io/notes/aspiring-academics/">Shashank Srikant: <em>Aspiring Academics</em></a></li>
  <li><a href="https://willcrichton.net/notes/making-the-most-out-of-cmu/">Will Crichton: <em>Making the most out of CMU</em></a></li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="a-little-on-me-">A Little on Me :)</h2>

<h3 id="why-i-care-about-undergrad-research">Why I Care About Undergrad Research</h3>

<p>As an undergrad, I was fortunate to have some outstanding mentors—including the
grad student I worked with and the professor who ran the group. Both shaped the
way I observe the world, tackle technical problems, and encouraged me to think
about how the work we do can make a real impact on the world.</p>

<p>Because I credit my mentors for any success I’ve had so far, I’ve felt it’s
important to try to give back and attempt to be to others what my mentors were
to me. For this reason, I’m always open to working with undergrads who are
interested in my field and are prepared to make a commitment to their work.</p>

<h3 id="why-i-emphasize-commitment-from-both-parties">Why I Emphasize Commitment (from both parties)</h3>

<p>I place a lot of importance on both parties (undergrad and grad student mentor)
making a serious commitment to their responsibilities.</p>

<ul>
  <li>For the grad student: this means spending time discussing problems, offering ideas, and providing general support.</li>
  <li>For the undergrad: this means independently learning the necessary tools and techniques and generating, testing, and evaluating their own ideas.</li>
</ul>

<p>One key realization I had in undergrad was that I needed to determine what my
priorities were and focus on them. At first, I was doing the bare minimum in
research and it wasn’t rewarding. Once I invested more time, the experience
became far more valuable. I want students working with me to feel that same
growth—and I want to feel that my time is being valued, too.</p>

<h3 id="why-i-want-peer-based-interactions">Why I Want Peer-Based Interactions</h3>

<p>As an undergrad, my mentors treated me as a peer. Even though it was obvious I
didn’t have the same expertise, my ideas were always respected. This allowed me
to ask questions and propose ideas freely, making our interactions both helpful
and enjoyable.</p>

<p>I aim to maintain this same peer-based dynamic with students I work with.</p>

<h3 id="why-its-okay-to-not-be-certain">Why It’s Okay to Not Be Certain</h3>

<p>I didn’t start in robotics. I first worked in a manufacturing research group and
planned to go into industry. It wasn’t until junior year—after taking a robotics
course—that my path changed. Mentors helped me pivot, and I want to do the same
for others.</p>

<p>If you’re not sure robotics is for you, that’s okay! As long as you’re committed
to seriously finding out, I’ll support you—whether you stay or transition
elsewhere.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="expectations">Expectations</h2>

<p>So far I’ve loosely discussed things like commitment, interactions, and support.
I’m going to try to make those statements more concrete here.
These are mostly framed for in-semester work but the sentiments apply to
out-of-semester work as well. Of course, the expected time commitment is
generally higher during the summer.</p>

<h3 id="time-commitment">Time Commitment</h3>

<p>From experience I’ve found that making notable progress generally requires a
planned commitment of at least 15 hours a week (more in the summer). I
understand some weeks may be less, and that life is unpredictable.  That’s
completely okay, just communicate this so that we’re on the same page.</p>

<h3 id="communications">Communications</h3>

<p>Communication channels should be crystal clear. I want for you to feel free to ask or
say anything. If you need anything - shoot me an email or drop by our lab. If you have any questions you’ve
been wondering - shoot me an email or drop by lab. If you feel like there is a better way I could support or
help you, please let me know!</p>

<h3 id="organization">Organization</h3>

<p>Some degree of organization is necessary. Many researchers are naturally disorganized (my-
self included at times). I’ve found that a minimum level of organization and documentation greatly benefits
productivity, communication, and the impact of work.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Keep organized notes of problems and solutions—it helps you and future contributors.</li>
  <li>Try to think of your work as a series of hypotheses and experiments to test them. Write
down your hypotheses, the experiments you plan to run, and the results you get.</li>
  <li>My old boss had a phrase, <em>“an engineer has done nothing until it has been documented”</em>.</li>
  <li>Use version control (e.g., git) to keep track of your code and experiments.</li>
  <li>Show up to discussions and meetings prepared. If you have questions, write them down
ahead of time so we can make the most of our time together.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="meetings">Meetings</h3>

<p>I like to have a recurring scheduled meeting (typically weekly) with undergrads and am generally
available to meet more to address technical issues, ideas, and questions that may arise.</p>

<h3 id="workspace">Workspace</h3>

<p>A lot of the work done in our group can be done remotely. However, I’ve found
that planning on working at least 60% of the time in our lab during normal
working hours is beneficial. This is because it reduces the friction on getting
help, learning from others, and getting integrated into the lab community.
Oftentimes asking a question in-person can lead to a much more informative or
insightful answer than a text- based conversation. That said, there is a time
and place for remote work and it’s your call on how/where you can be most
productive. I myself will occasionally avoid the lab to engage in long-duration
focused work (typically writing).</p>

<h3 id="credit">Credit</h3>

<p>If you do great work, I recognize it! I like to sing the praises of the great job done by people who
work with me. If your work is a serious contribution to a publication you will be made an author. I want
you to feel recognized and your work respected.</p>

<h3 id="abilities">Abilities</h3>

<p>As long as you are dedicated to putting the time in, I think pretty much
anything can be picked up as you go. I’m happy to help you learn whatever skills
are necessary and encourage any directions you want to work on.</p>

<p>I will say that some prior experience with programming and some level of
college-level math is generally helpful (though not always necessary).
These are definitely skills you should expect to learn and improve on working
with me.</p>

<h2 id="the-bottom-line">The Bottom Line</h2>

<p>Being an undergraduate researcher can—and should—be an amazing experience! But
it requires buy-in and commitment from both parties.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research" /><category term="skills" /><category term="research" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My beliefs on the points of undergrad research and what I expect from students.]]></summary></entry></feed>