<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://alanpapalia.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://alanpapalia.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2025-08-11T00:50:24+00:00</updated><id>https://alanpapalia.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">My Lab Philosophy as a (new) Faculty</title><link href="https://alanpapalia.github.io/blog/2025/advising-philosophy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Lab Philosophy as a (new) Faculty" /><published>2025-07-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alanpapalia.github.io/blog/2025/advising-philosophy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alanpapalia.github.io/blog/2025/advising-philosophy/"><![CDATA[<p>This is a mixture of:</p>
<ul>
  <li>my personal philosophy on a PhD and advisor/advisee relationships;</li>
  <li>my expectations for students in my lab;</li>
  <li>my expectations for myself as an advisor; and</li>
  <li>light discussion of structures and systems in the lab that support the above points.</li>
</ul>

<p>While this is primarily written for students interested in joining the lab, I
hope it’s also useful as a reference point for those evaluating different
advising styles more broadly.</p>

<hr />

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>What’s your advising philosophy?</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Ah, the classic question that seems to keep popping up.</p>

<p>I’ve been fortunate to learn from a range of mentors with very different
approaches - some deeply hands-on, other less so; some focused on technical
skills, others on big-picture thinking.  Across these experiences, I’ve tried to
pull out what I thought worked well and what didn’t. As such, this document
reflects the values and practices I hope to bring into my own advising, based
largely on my own experiences.</p>

<p>Of course, this is partly biased by what worked well <em>for me</em>. I’ve tried my
best to avoid this bias, by talking a lot with colleagues on their advising
experiences and reflecting on my own experiences as a mentor/advisor.</p>

<p>In one or two places, I will dive into some deeper details on how I try to structure
aspects and thought processes. These sections will be lower-level than the remainder
of this document, but I think they are useful to give a glimpse into the types of
structures that we will use in the lab to help develop and discuss ideas.</p>

<hr />

<h1 id="table-of-contents">Table of Contents</h1>

<ul>
  <li><a href="#table-of-contents">Table of Contents</a></li>
  <li><a href="#philosophy">Philosophy</a>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="#what-is-the-point-of-a-phd">What is the point of a PhD?</a></li>
      <li><a href="#defining-world-class-research">Defining world-class research</a></li>
      <li><a href="#the-magnitude-of-world-class-problems-and-the-myth-of-breakthroughs">The magnitude of “world-class problems” and the myth of breakthroughs</a>
        <ul>
          <li><a href="#how-to-evaluate-good-problems">How to evaluate good problems?</a></li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#expectation-setting-background-and-development">Expectation setting: background and development</a>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="#student-background">Student background</a></li>
      <li><a href="#student-technical-development">Student technical development</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#expectation-setting-what-problems-we-work-on">Expectation setting: what problems we work on</a>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="#working-outside-our-labs-core-areas">Working outside our lab’s core areas</a></li>
      <li><a href="#independence-and-choosing-research-topics">Independence and choosing research topics</a></li>
      <li><a href="#funding-and-research-direction">Funding and research direction</a></li>
      <li><a href="#proposing-ideas">Proposing ideas</a>
        <ul>
          <li><a href="#proposal-sketches">Proposal sketches</a></li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#expectation-setting-progress">Expectation setting: progress</a>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="#what-does-progress-look-like">What does progress look like?</a></li>
      <li><a href="#expectations-by-stage">Expectations by stage</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#expectation-setting-mentorship-and-communication">Expectation setting: mentorship and communication</a>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="#mentorship-style">Mentorship style</a></li>
      <li><a href="#communication">Communication</a></li>
      <li><a href="#feedback">Feedback</a></li>
      <li><a href="#how-to-meet">How to meet</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#misc-but-important">Misc. but important</a>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="#time-management-and-work-life-balance">Time management and work-life balance</a></li>
      <li><a href="#authorship-and-collaboration">Authorship and collaboration</a></li>
      <li><a href="#reproducibility-and-research-artifacts">Reproducibility and research artifacts</a></li>
      <li><a href="#internships-and-external-opportunities">Internships and external opportunities</a></li>
      <li><a href="#time-is-finite-my-limitations">Time is finite (my limitations)</a></li>
      <li><a href="#lab-structures-and-systems">Lab structures and systems</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#closing-notes">Closing Notes</a></li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h1 id="philosophy">Philosophy</h1>

<h2 id="what-is-the-point-of-a-phd">What is the point of a PhD?</h2>

<p>A PhD is a training ground for independent researchers. The goal is not just to
complete projects or publish papers, but to learn how to define problems, manage
uncertainty, and contribute new and meaningful ideas to the world.</p>

<p>My hope is that every student who comes through our lab leaves with the
ability (and confidence) to do world-class research. The best way to become
that kind of researcher is to try. Not through perfection or constant success,
but through thoughtful work, persistence, and ambition.</p>

<p>That said, a PhD is not a commitment to an academic career. The skills you’ll
develop - deep thinking, problem-solving, communication, and self-direction -
are valuable across many paths. I seriously considered leaving academia during
my PhD, and I think that reflection was healthy and important. I’ll support you
wherever your goals lead.</p>

<h2 id="defining-world-class-research">Defining world-class research</h2>

<p>When I say “world-class research,” I don’t mean publishing <em>n</em> papers per year
at top conferences. I mean work that is thoughtful, rigorous, and can stand the
test of time.</p>

<p>To me, that involves:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Identifying problems that matter - either practically or theoretically;</li>
  <li>Developing deep understanding of both the problem and the surrounding literature;</li>
  <li>Situating your work in the broader context of the field;</li>
  <li>Advancing knowledge through new ideas, theory, methods, or empirical results; and</li>
  <li>Communicating those contributions clearly and convincingly to others.</li>
</ul>

<p>That may sound abstract - and it is. Great research looks different in
different areas. Still, the core idea is simple: we aim to do careful work on
important questions, and share it in a way that others can understand, trust,
and build on.</p>

<p>To ground this philosophy, I want to share a personal example. One of the major
projects from my PhD was a new localization technique that removed a key
limitation present in much of the prior work. It took time to get there - longer
than many of the faster-turnaround projects my peers pursued - and once I had
the core result, I didn’t rush it out. I invested substantial time in writing,
analysis, and experimental validation to make sure the contribution was clear,
well-supported, and compelling. I wanted to really convince the community that
this was a meaningful advance.</p>

<p>Fast-forward some time and I receive an email telling me that the work received
the Best Paper Award from IEEE Transactions on Robotics, the flagship journal in
our field. More importantly, it remains one of the results I’m most proud of.
One carefully executed paper can shape a field (and a career) more than five
rushed ones.</p>

<p>This is the kind of work I want to enable. My hope is to create an environment
where students are supported in taking the time and space to pursue deep,
ambitious research that genuinely matters.</p>

<h2 id="the-magnitude-of-world-class-problems-and-the-myth-of-breakthroughs">The magnitude of “world-class problems” and the myth of breakthroughs</h2>

<p>Having defined what I mean by world-class research, I want to address a common
myth: the idea that you need to solve everything at once, or that every project
must be a breakthrough. Most reasonable people, after reflecting on this, recognize
this to be false but it still can often sit in the back of our minds and can
manifest as various forms of doubt, imposter syndrome, or perfectionism.</p>

<p>Major research problems - those that are impactful to society and push the our
understandings - rarely are solved in a single work. In practice, most real
progress comes through slow, deliberate work: refining ideas, uncovering
structure, building tools, and connecting dots over time.</p>

<p>What we often call a “breakthrough” is usually the result of accumulated
insight. It might be a paper that synthesizes prior work, reframes a problem in
a compelling way, bridges disciplines, or advances an existing line of inquiry -
but it often rests on years of less visible effort.</p>

<p>I say this because it’s easy to become paralyzed by the myth of the
breakthrough: the idea that if you’re not solving everything at once, your work
doesn’t matter. That’s false. Chipping away at hard problems is not just
acceptable - it’s the norm (just look at the history of deep learning).
Persistent, thoughtful progress is what good research usually looks like.</p>

<h3 id="how-to-evaluate-good-problems">How to evaluate good problems?</h3>

<p><em>Low-level discussion follows.</em></p>

<p>There’s no single formula for what makes a good research problem - but there are
useful patterns. One framework I like (shared by Robert Mahony) evaluates
problems along five axes:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Impact</strong>: Is this problem important? Will solving it matter to others - scientifically, societally, or practically?</li>
  <li><strong>Novelty</strong>: Does it advance how we think about a problem? Does it offer a new perspective, method, or insight?</li>
  <li><strong>Feasibility</strong>: Can we make real progress in a reasonable amount of time? Is the scope right - not too narrow, not too vast?</li>
  <li><strong>Interest</strong>: Are you genuinely excited by it? Will you care enough to stick with it when it gets hard?</li>
  <li><strong>Resources</strong>: Do we have (or can we find) the tools, time, and collaborators needed to work on it effectively?</li>
</ul>

<p>The balance of these factors changes over time. For a first-year student,
feasibility and interest often matter most - especially when building confidence
and momentum. Your first project doesn’t have to be world-changing. My own first
research problem wasn’t that impactful but it gave me a solid foundation to
build on.</p>

<p>Choosing good problems is a really important topic, so for more discussion of this
I recommend checking out my <a href="/blog/2025/phd-advice/">collection of PhD advice</a>.
There’s a lot of writing on this and the existing corpus of advice is largely in
agreement, so I won’t go into any more detail here.</p>

<h1 id="expectation-setting-background-and-development">Expectation setting: background and development</h1>

<h2 id="student-background">Student background</h2>

<p>Of course, nobody shows up knowing everything.  I generally do not expect a very
specific background from students, as I think that effort, motivation, and
working intelligently are more important than having a specific set of skills
from the get-go.  A key part of your PhD will be building new technical skills -
especially in areas like optimization, probability, machine learning, and
robotics systems. This is going to be difficult, but highly rewarding.</p>

<p>You will need to take ownership of that growth: reading, implementing,
debugging, asking questions, and seeking out gaps in your own understanding.
That’s part of what it means to become an independent researcher.</p>

<p>That said, it is very helpful for students to arrive with a solid foundation
in programming and a willingness to engage deeply with mathematics and systems
engineering. At some point in your PhD, you will likely spend substantial time
on all of these topics, so a good base (and more importantly, knowing that you
enjoy doing these things) will go a long way.</p>

<h2 id="student-technical-development">Student technical development</h2>

<p>While you’re responsible for your growth, you won’t be doing it in a vacuum. A
high functioning lab provides a supportive environment for learning. Some things
the lab will provide include:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Reading groups focused on foundational topics and emerging research;</li>
  <li>Weekly group meetings that include technical talks and project updates;</li>
  <li>Shared tools, codebases, and best practices;</li>
  <li>Opportunities to work with and learn from more senior students and collaborators;</li>
  <li>Regular one-on-one meetings where I can recommend resources, help unblock technical challenges, etc.</li>
</ul>

<p>Note that while the group is young, I will be more directly involved in all of
these activities. I.e., I will be involved in reading group and technical
discussions.</p>

<p>There will also inevitably be types of mentorship that I cannot provide (e.g.,
specific expertise in a niche area, or the perspective of a senior researcher).
In these instances, I will do my best to connect you with others who can help.
It is helpful here if you can identify what you need and ask for it.</p>

<h1 id="expectation-setting-what-problems-we-work-on">Expectation setting: what problems we work on</h1>

<h2 id="working-outside-our-labs-core-areas">Working outside our lab’s core areas</h2>

<p>For many reasons, it makes sense to do work that can draw on the core competencies
of our lab. This has both scientific benefit (we can make a sustained push along
a particular line of inquiry) and practical benefit (we can leverage in-house
expertise, tools, and resources).</p>

<p>However, it is also important to explore ideas outside our core areas. This can
lead to new insights, unexpected connections, and open up new research
directions. This type of exploration is encouraged, though it should be done
thoughtfully and strategically. This type of work is taking a bit more of a shot
in the dark, so it is useful to think through the risks, payoffs, and possible
fallbacks before diving in.</p>

<p>Ideally, the research we do should be a bit of a mix of the two: bringing new
outside ideas into our core areas, and applying our core skills to new domains.</p>

<p>And if you ever feel stuck - whether it’s a paper you don’t understand, a system
that won’t work, or a gap in your background - please ask. You’re not expected
to already know everything. You’re expected to be proactive, resourceful, and
willing to learn. I may not have the answers, but I can help you find
resources, suggest approaches, or connect you with others who can help. This sounds
obvious, but I think worth re-iterating.</p>

<h2 id="independence-and-choosing-research-topics">Independence and choosing research topics</h2>

<p>A core goal of the PhD is learning how to define and pursue your own research
agenda. My role is to help you get there - by guiding problem selection early on,
helping develop your ideas, and offering strategic feedback as your independence
grows.</p>

<p>Early in the program, I’ll likely suggest a few well-scoped problems to help you
gain traction. These are meant to build technical skills, familiarity with the
literature, and confidence. Over time, I expect students to take increasing
ownership: identifying research questions, framing them clearly, designing
experiments or theory, and driving day-to-day progress.</p>

<p>Even the most senior researchers seek feedback and collaboration. But by the
later stages of your PhD, you should be operating independently, with me acting
more as a sounding board - someone who can help refine ideas, flag blind spots,
and challenge assumptions.</p>

<h2 id="funding-and-research-direction">Funding and research direction</h2>

<p>Like any lab, our research will be shaped in part by funding opportunities. I
work actively to secure support that aligns with our scientific interests and
values, and I aim to keep student-led inquiry at the center of our work.</p>

<p>In robotics, most funding agencies allow significant flexibility in how research
goals are pursued. That flexibility is something I take seriously. When we
propose work to a sponsor, I try to frame it in a way that reflects our broader
interests so that there is room for exploration, creativity, and intellectual
ownership by students.</p>

<p>In practice, this often means that:</p>
<ul>
  <li>You will have space to define your own research directions, even within funded projects;</li>
  <li>We can typically carve out subproblems or extensions of a project that align closely with your interests;</li>
  <li>If a project ever feels too constrained, we will work together to find a better framing or explore adjacent ideas that satisfy both the scientific and sponsor goals.</li>
</ul>

<p>I will also actively pursue more flexible or exploratory sources of funding,
such as university seed grants or fellowships to support student-initiated
ideas.</p>

<p>At the end of the day, I want you to work on problems that you find exciting and
important. We’ll be strategic about matching those ideas to funding
opportunities, but the driving force should always be meaningful research, not
just fulfilling a contract.</p>

<h2 id="proposing-ideas">Proposing ideas</h2>

<p>I expect students to start proposing their own ideas from day one. Problem
formulation is a core research skill. This takes time, feedback, and repeated
practice to develop.</p>

<p>In my own PhD experience, one of the most valuable aspects of our lab culture
was that students were expected to take intellectual ownership of their work. It
was hard - especially early on - but that challenge accelerated my growth as a
researcher and independent thinker. I aim to foster a similar environment.</p>

<p>Your early ideas don’t need to be polished or correct. What matters is engaging
actively with the research process: spotting gaps, questioning assumptions, and
thinking creatively about where to go next.</p>

<h3 id="proposal-sketches">Proposal sketches</h3>

<p><em>Low-level discussion follows.</em></p>

<p>One you have some medium confidence and high interest in a problem, it is good
to try to formalize it into a (very brief) proposal. This is a particularly
good exercise for first-year students, but is encouraged for all students.
This should be a ~1-2 page document that outlines:</p>
<ul>
  <li>The problem you want to solve</li>
  <li>Why it matters (impact)</li>
  <li>How it relates to existing work (literature and novelty)</li>
  <li>A sketch of your approach (methods)</li>
  <li>What would success look like (evaluation)</li>
  <li>What resources you need (time, tools, collaborators)</li>
  <li>What skills you need to develop (background, tools, etc.)</li>
  <li>Any initial thoughts on feasibility and risks</li>
</ul>

<p>This proposal doesn’t have to be a pristine piece of writing, just communicate
the ideas clearly and give us a shared understanding of what you want to do. We
can iterate on it together.</p>

<p>If there are gaps you are having trouble filling in the proposal, we can also
try to close them together. A lot of the proposal writing process is about
critically thinking about the problem and how you want to approach it, to force
you to face what is currently unclear and to structure your thoughts.</p>

<p>This is largely related to the
<a href="https://www.darpa.mil/about/heilmeier-catechism">Heilmeier Catechism</a>,
which is a popular framework for constructing and evaluating research proposals.</p>

<h1 id="expectation-setting-progress">Expectation setting: progress</h1>

<h2 id="what-does-progress-look-like">What does progress look like?</h2>

<p>Progress in research is often nonlinear and unpredictable. Some weeks feel like
breakthroughs, others are spent debugging a tool, reading papers, or reframing
the problem entirely. That’s normal.</p>

<p>Two questions can help you reflect on whether you’re moving forward:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Time</strong>: Are you consistently spending focused time on your research?</li>
  <li><strong>Value</strong>: Is that time moving your project or understanding in a meaningful direction?</li>
</ul>

<p>Not all progress looks like new results. It can include:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Developing a deeper understanding of the literature;</li>
  <li>Asking sharper and more focused research questions;</li>
  <li>Writing or refactoring tools that improve your workflow;</li>
  <li>Explaining your work more clearly than before;</li>
  <li>Gaining autonomy in how you scope, plan, and execute your work.</li>
</ul>

<p>One of the most valuable weeks I spent during my PhD involved nothing but
reading. I went deep into the literature for my specific field, identified
patterns and gaps that weren’t commonly acknowledged by other practitioners, and
developed a much clearer view of where my work could contribute. I wrote no
code, proved no theorems, and produced no paper. Still, this time fundamentally
shaped my future research and gave me the necessary background to make
meaningful progress.</p>

<p>In my mind, one key is to - with some frequency - ask: <em>What is the best use of my time right now?</em> And then
act on that. Don’t do this every day, otherwise you will never get anything done. But do it often enough that you are
relatively confident that you are working on the right things.</p>

<p>At a high level, some soft benchmarks can be useful. A common goal is to
contribute to 2–3 paper submissions per year, including both first-author and
collaborative work. But this is not a hard rule. One strong, well-executed paper
may matter more than several minor ones, and some years will be heavier on
exploration, learning, or tool-building. A PhD should have a minimum of 3-4
good first-author papers.</p>

<h2 id="expectations-by-stage">Expectations by stage</h2>

<p>This is a rough outline of what I expect from students at different stages of
their PhD. Of course, every student and project is different, so this is just a
general guideline. We’ll adapt it to fit your specific situation and goals
(and departmental requirements, if relevant).</p>

<p><strong>Year 1</strong>: Focus on building technical skills, understanding the literature,
and developing confidence in your ability to define and pursue research
problems. A great goal is to complete a first project that results in a paper
submission. This could be a small but well-scoped problem that you can execute
independently with some guidance. You should also be able to explain your work
clearly and articulate its contributions.</p>

<p><strong>Year 2-3</strong>: You should just be getting the abilities to independently scope and
execute an interesting project. I will provide guidance on topics like framing,
methodology, and potential pitfalls, but you should be in the driver’s seat
for project scoping.
If there are certain areas to explore, collaborations to
start, or tools to build, this can be a good time to do so. Midway through year
2, I strongly suggest you start drafting a proposal for your thesis topic.  This
is not a final declaration of the work you will do - it can change completely
and parts can be added or removed - but this is the time to start really
establishing this high-level vision for what you want to do.</p>

<p><strong>Year 4+</strong>: By this point, you should be operating largely independently,
with me acting as a sounding board for ideas, feedback on papers, and high-level
guidance. You should be able to define your own research agenda, identify
important problems, and execute projects with minimal oversight. My goal here is
to enable you to do your best work (likely by largely stepping back and giving
you the space and resources needed).</p>

<h1 id="expectation-setting-mentorship-and-communication">Expectation setting: mentorship and communication</h1>

<h2 id="mentorship-style">Mentorship style</h2>

<p>There’s no one-size-fits-all approach to mentoring. Every student is different,
and my style will adapt to fit your goals, working style, and stage of progress.
That said, there are core principles that guide how I work with students:</p>

<p><strong>Student development</strong>: As you progress, I expect you to take increasing
ownership of your research - choosing problems, developing ideas, and charting
your own path with growing independence.</p>

<p><strong>Independence</strong>: I’ll provide mentorship, structure, and feedback - but I expect
students to be self-directed, take initiative, and actively drive their own
learning and progress. The whole point of a PhD is to learn how to do
independent research.</p>

<p><strong>Whole-person support</strong>: PhD students are people. I care about your
well-being, not just your productivity. If you’re struggling - with work,
health, family, or motivation - I want you to be able to bring that up. We can
adjust, recalibrate, and figure out how to move forward in a sustainable way.</p>

<p><strong>Level of involvement</strong>: I aim to be an engaged mentor, especially early on. I
expect to work closely with students on ideas, experiments, and papers. As you
grow more confident and experienced, I’ll step back and give you more space.
We’ll calibrate together how much guidance and feedback is helpful at each
stage.</p>

<p><strong>What I’ll work on with you</strong>: I will help
scope problems, refine ideas, and discuss experimental design. I also put
a strong emphasis on communication skills. I’ll work with you on writing, giving
talks, and clearly articulating your contributions.</p>

<p><strong>Communication and calibration</strong>: I will be transparent about my
expectations, and I’ll ask you to do the same. I want you to raise questions if
expectations or ideas are unclear. Open, regular communication is
key to building a productive advising relationship - and to making sure you’re
getting the right kind of support at the right time.</p>

<p><strong>Career development</strong>: I’ll support you in whatever path you choose: academia,
industry, startups, or elsewhere. That includes helping find opportunities,
preparing applications, doing mock interviews, and connecting you with
colleagues in relevant fields, companies, and institutions.</p>

<h2 id="communication">Communication</h2>

<p>Clear, frequent communication is critical for good advising. I aim to meet with
each student regularly - typically once per week - to discuss research updates,
give feedback, and help work through open questions. These meetings are also a
space to talk about broader topics like career planning, skill development, or
general questions about research.</p>

<p>Communication shouldn’t be limited to scheduled meetings. I encourage you to
reach out (Slack or email) when you’re stuck, excited about a new idea, or
unsure how to proceed. You don’t need a polished result to start a conversation.
Often the best discussions come from messy, unfinished thoughts.</p>

<p>I try to be responsive and available, especially during crunch periods. If
something is urgent or time-sensitive (e.g., for a deadline or blocking issue),
just flag it clearly and I’ll prioritize it.</p>

<h2 id="feedback">Feedback</h2>

<p>Feedback and iteration is at the center of doing good research. Nothing is
correct on the first try (including this document).</p>

<p>I give direct, detailed feedback - particularly on writing, presentations, and
framing research ideas. I take your work seriously, and my goal is to push you
to think clearly, sharpen your arguments, and communicate precisely. One of the
greatest complements given to researchers is that they are “clear thinkers.”
This is very much a trainable skill, and I want all students to develop it.</p>

<p>One of the most productive things you can do is help me understand what kind of
feedback you want. Are you looking for high-level input on direction, or line
edits on a nearly-final talk? Are you trying to decide between ideas, or polish
a contribution? Letting me know helps me meet you where you are.</p>

<p>Also, the status of your work matters. A rough draft invites different
comments than a polished one. If you want feedback on a specific aspect, let me
know. I’m happy to help you refine your ideas, but I can only do that if
I understand what you’re looking for.</p>

<p>I also welcome disagreement. If you think I’m wrong about something, say so.
Research is about making arguments and having those arguments tested. Thoughtful
pushback is a sign that you’re thinking deeply and independently.</p>

<p>Ultimately, I want our communication to be honest, frequent, and intellectually
engaged. If anything ever feels off, please bring it up. Feedback should go both
ways.</p>

<h2 id="how-to-meet">How to meet</h2>

<p>Spending a little bit of time before meetings can make them much more productive.
It is good to have a list of prioritized topics to discuss. If you send them ahead of
time I can also prepare some thoughts or resources in advance.</p>

<p>If there is a problem you are facing, it can be really helpful if you can answer
a few questions before we meet:</p>
<ul>
  <li>What have you tried so far?</li>
  <li>What is getting in the way of tackling this?</li>
  <li>What support do you need?</li>
  <li>What would you do if you were in my seat?</li>
  <li>Is there anything else I should know?</li>
</ul>

<p>This helps me understand the context, quickly rule out any obvious solutions that
you have already tried, and focus our discussion on how I can best support you.</p>

<h1 id="misc-but-important">Misc. but important</h1>

<h2 id="time-management-and-work-life-balance">Time management and work-life balance</h2>

<p>A PhD is a marathon, not a sprint. I expect students to work hard and take their
research seriously, but I also expect you to rest, take care of yourself, and
maintain a life outside the lab. Sustainable progress comes from consistency,
not burnout.</p>

<p>There will occasionally be intense pushes before deadlines, but those should be
rare, not the default. If you’re feeling overwhelmed or burned out, I want to
hear about it. We can revisit timelines, adjust priorities, and find a better
pace. Long-term health (mental and physical) is important.</p>

<h2 id="authorship-and-collaboration">Authorship and collaboration</h2>

<p>I believe in giving credit where credit is due. If you contribute meaningfully
to a project (through ideas, implementation, writing, or experimentation) you
should be recognized as a co-author. I generally follow common authorship
conventions in robotics, but I’m always open to discussing authorship decisions
transparently and early.</p>

<p>I also strongly encourage collaboration - both within our lab and across labs,
institutions, and disciplines. Many of the best ideas emerge from unexpected
conversations, and I’ll support you in building those connections and pursuing
joint work when it advances the science.</p>

<h2 id="reproducibility-and-research-artifacts">Reproducibility and research artifacts</h2>

<p>Our goal is to produce research that others can build on. This means writing
clean, well-documented code, organizing experiments clearly, and making results
reproducible.</p>

<p>I do not expect perfection, but I do expect students to value clarity,
maintainability, and reusability in their code and data practices. If others
can’t understand, reproduce, or build on your work, it limits its impact.</p>

<h2 id="internships-and-external-opportunities">Internships and external opportunities</h2>

<p>Many students find value in internships or external research opportunities
during their PhD. I spent a summer during my PhD as an intern, and it helped
reaffirm my interest in academic research. I did not serve as a visiting student
(or similar) during my PhD, but know many people who did and were able to get
a lot out of it.</p>

<p>If these are of interest to you, I’m happy to support these opportunities.  I’m
lucky to have a network of colleagues in industry and academia, and I can make
introductions where appropriate.</p>

<h2 id="time-is-finite-my-limitations">Time is finite (my limitations)</h2>

<p>In an ideal world, I would have unlimited time to work with each student,
providing detailed feedback on every idea, paper, and experiment. In reality,
time is finite. I have many different responsibilities, including teaching,
administration, fundraising, and service. It’s also important to me to
spend time with my family (and students should similarly value time outside the lab).</p>

<p>As such, while I will do my best to support you, this only works if you take
ownership of your work. I will do what I can to support you, provide feedback,
and help you grow as a researcher, but I expect you to come prepared to
meetings, actively drive your own research, and take initiative in your own
development.</p>

<p>At the end of the day, we will both be time-limited. I will do my best to
prioritize my time to help you and to make the best use of your time. In
exchange, I ask that you be proactive, resourceful, and try to do the same for
me. One of the great skills of a PhD is learning how to “manage up” - i.e., how to
get the most out of your advisor’s time and expertise. This is a skill that will
serve you well in your career, so I encourage you to practice it.</p>

<h2 id="lab-structures-and-systems">Lab structures and systems</h2>

<p>Because of the constraints on time, a lot of my life is spent in prioritization
and efficiency mode. Many of the lab structures and systems I put in place are
designed to help us all work efficiently and effectively.  I generally believe
in minimal bureaucracy and structures, and I try to only put systems into place
that help focus thoughts in an efficient way with minimal overhead.
If the lab structures aren’t serving that purpose, we should find a system that
does.</p>

<h1 id="closing-notes">Closing Notes</h1>

<p>Grad school should be fun! It’s not easy, but it should be intellectually
rewarding and personally fulfilling. I loved my PhD experience, and I hope to
create an environment where you can equally enjoy the experience. I will do what
I can to create an enjoyable, productive, and intellectually rich environment and
I will ask you to do the same.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research" /><category term="skills" /><category term="research" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A collection of thoughts and expectations for students interested in my lab.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Advice for PhD students</title><link href="https://alanpapalia.github.io/blog/2025/phd-advice/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Advice for PhD students" /><published>2025-07-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alanpapalia.github.io/blog/2025/phd-advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alanpapalia.github.io/blog/2025/phd-advice/"><![CDATA[<p>There’s a lot of great advice out there for PhD students. Here I try to compile
some of the best advice I’ve come across, along with my own thoughts on the
matter. This is a living document, and I will update it as I find more advice or
as my own views evolve.</p>

<p>Of course, I don’t fully agree with all of this (and I couldn’t if I wanted to
– some of the points in these resources are slightly contradictory). However, I
mostly agree with the spirit of these points, and I think that it is worth
understanding the perspective they come from.</p>

<p>Take things with grains of salt, and think critically about what matches your
system. Most of all, remember that a PhD is supposed to be fun (albeit often
type two fun – not always “fun” in the moment, but deeply rewarding in
hindsight). If you find yourself not enjoying it, take a step back and think
about why that is.</p>

<p><strong>Last updated:</strong> July 8, 2025</p>

<h1 id="most-recommended-reads">Most Recommended Reads</h1>

<p>Here are the articles that I would most strongly recommend to current/aspiring PhD students (of course biased by my own beliefs):</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://michaelnielsen.org/blog/principles-of-effective-research/">Michael Nielsen’s Principles of Effective Research</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.jeanyang.com/posts/genius-fallacy/">Jean Yang’s the Genius Fallacy</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://jxyzabc.blogspot.com/2016/09/five-things-more-important-about.html">Jean Yang’s Five Things More Important About a Research Project Than Being in Love</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://greatresearch.org/2013/08/14/managing-your-advisor/">Managing Your Advisor</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.cs.unc.edu/~azuma/hitch4.html">So Long and Thanks for the PhD</a></li>
</ul>

<p>Of course, everything on this page is worth reading. If you’re time-constrained, I would recommend starting with the above.</p>

<h1 id="stories-of-a-phd">Stories of a PhD</h1>

<p>People who have written about their PhD experiences (benefit of hindsight):</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="/assets/pdf/philipguo-phd-grind.pdf">Philip Guo’s The PhD Grind</a> (this is a .pdf)</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="meta-phd-and-broad-phd-advice">Meta-PhD and Broad-PhD Advice</h1>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://karpathy.github.io/2016/09/07/phd/">Andrej Karpathy’s PhD Survival Guide</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://michaelnielsen.org/blog/principles-of-effective-research/">Michael Nielsen’s Principles of Effective Research</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://greatresearch.org/2013/08/23/why-get-a-ph-d/">Why Get a PhD?</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.cs.unc.edu/~azuma/hitch4.html">So Long and Thanks for the PhD</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://greatresearch.org/2013/08/14/managing-your-advisor/">Managing Your Advisor</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://greatresearch.org/2013/09/13/cultivating-your-research-taste/">Cultivating Your Research Taste</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fqPSnjewkuA">Graduate School: Keys to Success</a> (video)</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.cs.virginia.edu/~robins/YouAndYourResearch.html">The classic Richard Hamming “You and Your Research” talk</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://greatresearch.org/2013/09/20/research-patterns/">Research Patterns</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.alextamkin.com/essays/tips-for-new-researchers">Alex Tamkin’s tips for researchers</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.quora.com/For-a-beginning-PhD-student-what-is-the-best-predictor-of-whether-or-not-that-student-will-continue-in-academia-beyond-the-PhD/answer/Ben-Y-Zhao?srid=uFKg&amp;share=1">What matters in PhD students?</a></li>
</ul>

<h1 id="persistence-and-motivation">Persistence and Motivation</h1>

<p>This shows up <strong>a lot</strong> in the advice above, but these are more specific discussions of the topic.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.jeanyang.com/posts/genius-fallacy/">Jean Yang’s the Genius Fallacy</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://jxyzabc.blogspot.com/2016/03/the-angst-overhead.html">Jean Yang’s The Angst Overhead</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://jxyzabc.blogspot.com/2016/09/five-things-more-important-about.html">Jean Yang’s Five Things More Important About a Research Project Than Being in Love</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://calnewport.com/the-passion-trap-how-the-search-for-your-lifes-work-is-making-your-working-life-miserable/">Cal Newport’s “The Passion Trap”</a></li>
</ul>

<h1 id="writing-and-communication">Writing and Communication</h1>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://greatresearch.org/2013/10/04/presenting-a-technical-talk/">Presenting a Technical Talk</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://greatresearch.org/2013/10/11/storytelling-101-writing-tips-for-academics/">Storytelling 101: Writing Tips for Academics</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://greatresearch.org/2013/09/06/you-and-your-research-proposal/">You and Your Research Proposal</a></li>
</ul>

<h1 id="reading-and-reviewing">Reading and Reviewing</h1>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://greatresearch.org/2013/10/18/the-paper-reviewing-process/">The Paper Reviewing Process</a></li>
</ul>

<h1 id="interested-in-an-academic-career">Interested in an Academic Career?</h1>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://danieltakeshi.github.io/2023/06/15/faculty-application">Daniel Seita’s Experience with the Faculty Job Market</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://sylviaherbert.com/faculty-application-advice/">Sylvia Herbert’s Advice for the Academic Job Market</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research-advice" /><category term="research-advice" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A collection of advice for PhD students.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Undergrad Research Philosophy</title><link href="https://alanpapalia.github.io/blog/2025/undergrad-research/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Undergrad Research Philosophy" /><published>2025-07-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alanpapalia.github.io/blog/2025/undergrad-research</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alanpapalia.github.io/blog/2025/undergrad-research/"><![CDATA[<p>This is a document I wrote early on in grad school to help me clarify my
philosophy on working with undergrads. I haven’t really updated it since my
first or second year (2020?), but I still think it captures my beliefs on the
points of undergrad research and what I expect from students.</p>

<hr />

<h1 id="my-undergrad-research-philosophy">My Undergrad Research Philosophy</h1>

<p>If you’re reading this, there’s a high probability that you’re an undergrad who
is interested in research in robotics. That’s great! Robotics is an exciting
field to work in right now, with really bright people and really important
problems we’re trying to solve!</p>

<p>All the flashy demos online make it seem like there aren’t any unanswered
questions in the field, but if you ask around, you’ll discover there’s so much
work left to do—and the field needs bright, energetic minds like you to help
solve them!</p>

<p>I love working with undergrads (and grad students) who are excited to tackle
problems. This document outlines the <em>what</em> and <em>why</em> behind my undergrad
collaborations. I know this is a bit of a read, but if you’re seriously
interested in trying out this research thing, I ask that you give it a genuine
read through. Part of working together is we both are committing time to this
collaboration, which really works best if we’re on the same page as to what that
means.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="resources">Resources</h2>

<p>Before diving into my own ramblings, here are some really great blog posts that
I very much agree with. Before you do anything else, I’d encourage you to read
through these and think about how their ideas sit with your own philosophies. I
don’t think it’s a coincidence that these separate blog posts all came to
relatively similar conclusions about getting the most out of undergrad research.
Based on my own experiences, these ideas extend beyond just research but really
getting the most out of your time as an undergrad in general.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://rosewang2008.github.io/blog/2021/01/03/undergrad-research-advice.html">Rose Wang: <em>Dear future undergraduate researcher</em></a></li>
  <li><a href="https://dblalock.github.io/how-to-undergrad-research/">Davis Blalock: <em>How to undergrad research</em></a></li>
  <li><a href="https://shashank-srikant.github.io/notes/aspiring-academics/">Shashank Srikant: <em>Aspiring Academics</em></a></li>
  <li><a href="https://willcrichton.net/notes/making-the-most-out-of-cmu/">Will Crichton: <em>Making the most out of CMU</em></a></li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="a-little-on-me-">A Little on Me :)</h2>

<h3 id="why-i-care-about-undergrad-research">Why I Care About Undergrad Research</h3>

<p>As an undergrad, I was fortunate to have some outstanding mentors—including the
grad student I worked with and the professor who ran the group. Both shaped the
way I observe the world, tackle technical problems, and encouraged me to think
about how the work we do can make a real impact on the world.</p>

<p>Because I credit my mentors for any success I’ve had so far, I’ve felt it’s
important to try to give back and attempt to be to others what my mentors were
to me. For this reason, I’m always open to working with undergrads who are
interested in my field and are prepared to make a commitment to their work.</p>

<h3 id="why-i-emphasize-commitment-from-both-parties">Why I Emphasize Commitment (from both parties)</h3>

<p>I place a lot of importance on both parties (undergrad and grad student mentor)
making a serious commitment to their responsibilities.</p>

<ul>
  <li>For the grad student: this means spending time discussing problems, offering ideas, and providing general support.</li>
  <li>For the undergrad: this means independently learning the necessary tools and techniques and generating, testing, and evaluating their own ideas.</li>
</ul>

<p>One key realization I had in undergrad was that I needed to determine what my
priorities were and focus on them. At first, I was doing the bare minimum in
research and it wasn’t rewarding. Once I invested more time, the experience
became far more valuable. I want students working with me to feel that same
growth—and I want to feel that my time is being valued, too.</p>

<h3 id="why-i-want-peer-based-interactions">Why I Want Peer-Based Interactions</h3>

<p>As an undergrad, my mentors treated me as a peer. Even though it was obvious I
didn’t have the same expertise, my ideas were always respected. This allowed me
to ask questions and propose ideas freely, making our interactions both helpful
and enjoyable.</p>

<p>I aim to maintain this same peer-based dynamic with students I work with.</p>

<h3 id="why-its-okay-to-not-be-certain">Why It’s Okay to Not Be Certain</h3>

<p>I didn’t start in robotics. I first worked in a manufacturing research group and
planned to go into industry. It wasn’t until junior year—after taking a robotics
course—that my path changed. Mentors helped me pivot, and I want to do the same
for others.</p>

<p>If you’re not sure robotics is for you, that’s okay! As long as you’re committed
to seriously finding out, I’ll support you—whether you stay or transition
elsewhere.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="expectations">Expectations</h2>

<p>So far I’ve loosely discussed things like commitment, interactions, and support.
I’m going to try to make those statements more concrete here.
These are mostly framed for in-semester work but the sentiments apply to
out-of-semester work as well. Of course, the expected time commitment is
generally higher during the summer.</p>

<h3 id="time-commitment">Time Commitment</h3>

<p>From experience I’ve found that making notable progress generally requires a
planned commitment of at least 15 hours a week (more in the summer). I
understand some weeks may be less, and that life is unpredictable.  That’s
completely okay, just communicate this so that we’re on the same page.</p>

<h3 id="communications">Communications</h3>

<p>Communication channels should be crystal clear. I want for you to feel free to ask or
say anything. If you need anything - shoot me an email or drop by our lab. If you have any questions you’ve
been wondering - shoot me an email or drop by lab. If you feel like there is a better way I could support or
help you, please let me know!</p>

<h3 id="organization">Organization</h3>

<p>Some degree of organization is necessary. Many researchers are naturally disorganized (my-
self included at times). I’ve found that a minimum level of organization and documentation greatly benefits
productivity, communication, and the impact of work.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Keep organized notes of problems and solutions—it helps you and future contributors.</li>
  <li>Try to think of your work as a series of hypotheses and experiments to test them. Write
down your hypotheses, the experiments you plan to run, and the results you get.</li>
  <li>My old boss had a phrase, <em>“an engineer has done nothing until it has been documented”</em>.</li>
  <li>Use version control (e.g., git) to keep track of your code and experiments.</li>
  <li>Show up to discussions and meetings prepared. If you have questions, write them down
ahead of time so we can make the most of our time together.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="meetings">Meetings</h3>

<p>I like to have a recurring scheduled meeting (typically weekly) with undergrads and am generally
available to meet more to address technical issues, ideas, and questions that may arise.</p>

<h3 id="workspace">Workspace</h3>

<p>A lot of the work done in our group can be done remotely. However, I’ve found
that planning on working at least 60% of the time in our lab during normal
working hours is beneficial. This is because it reduces the friction on getting
help, learning from others, and getting integrated into the lab community.
Oftentimes asking a question in-person can lead to a much more informative or
insightful answer than a text- based conversation. That said, there is a time
and place for remote work and it’s your call on how/where you can be most
productive. I myself will occasionally avoid the lab to engage in long-duration
focused work (typically writing).</p>

<h3 id="credit">Credit</h3>

<p>If you do great work, I recognize it! I like to sing the praises of the great job done by people who
work with me. If your work is a serious contribution to a publication you will be made an author. I want
you to feel recognized and your work respected.</p>

<h3 id="abilities">Abilities</h3>

<p>As long as you are dedicated to putting the time in, I think pretty much
anything can be picked up as you go. I’m happy to help you learn whatever skills
are necessary and encourage any directions you want to work on.</p>

<p>I will say that some prior experience with programming and some level of
college-level math is generally helpful (though not always necessary).
These are definitely skills you should expect to learn and improve on working
with me.</p>

<h2 id="the-bottom-line">The Bottom Line</h2>

<p>Being an undergraduate researcher can—and should—be an amazing experience! But
it requires buy-in and commitment from both parties.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research-advice" /><category term="research-advice" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My beliefs on the points of undergrad research and what I expect from students.]]></summary></entry></feed>